<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary PUBLIC '-//OASIS/DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN' 'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % user SYSTEM 'user.ent'>
%user;
]>
<glossary id='terminology'> <title>Terminology</title>

<glossdiv><title>A</title>
<glossentry id='g_active_depiction'><glossterm>Active Depiction</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>depiction</primary><secondary>active</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
The current depiction you are working on.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_allied_models'><glossterm>Allied Models</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>allied model</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Models which are run by the FPA, using data from the FPA, to generate other data (for example, ocean wave models).
The models are usually developed elsewhere.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_attributes'><glossterm>Attributes</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>attribute</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Attributes are optional parameters which can be attached to any feature in an FPA field.
For example, a minimum in the pressure field could be identified as a tropical storm, with a name and a radius of influence.
Similarly, one could indicate the speed and intensity of a cold front.
</para><para>
The ability to assign attributes to areas is particularly useful in aviation forecasting.
For example, forecasters can attach attributes to a cloud area such as cloud amount, cloud type, base of cloud, top of cloud, surface weather and visibility, icing or any other desired parameter.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>B</title>
<glossentry id='g_backup'><glossterm>Backup</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>backup</primary></indexterm>
<para>
A backup is created every time you save a field.
The number of days for which the field is retained is set in the setup file (contact System Administrator to change this).
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>C</title>
<glossentry id='g_coview'><glossterm>CoView</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>coview</primary></indexterm>
<para>
This feature lets you view the workspace of another depiction.
(You cannot edit the other depiction, however.) Use this to share your work with other FPA users.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>D</title>
<glossentry id='g_daily_fields'><glossterm>Daily Fields</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>field</primary><secondary>daily</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
Daily fields are fields which are valid for a specific day (for example, maximum temperature).
The time range of a daily field may span more than one depiction.
See <xref linkend='the_fpa_model'/>.
Daily fields are not interpolated, but can be edited.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_depiction'><glossterm>Depiction</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>depiction</primary></indexterm>
<para>
A depiction is your workspace; it is a graphic image of the geographic area overlaid with specific weather fields.
Load fields into depictions and then modify a sequence of depictions to describe the forecast weather.
Each depiction is valid for a specific date and time.
See <xref linkend='the_fpa_model'/>.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_depiction_sequence'><glossterm>Depiction Sequence</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>depiction</primary><secondary>sequence</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
A depiction sequence is a time ordered set of depictions.
A depiction can be thought of as a keyframe in a movie.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>E</title>
<glossentry id='g_elements'><glossterm>Elements</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>elements</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Elements are atmospheric parameters such as pressure, temperature or u/v component wind.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>F</title>
<glossentry id='g_features'><glossterm>Features</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>feature</primary></indexterm>
<para>
A feature is a recognizable shape or pattern in a data field.
For example, the shape of contours that delineate a low pressure centre represent a "feature" of the pressure field.
Similarly, the shape of an area of rain represents a feature of the precipitation field.
Forecasters rely heavily on the remarkable ability of the human mind to recognize features in data.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_fields'><glossterm>Fields</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>field</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Fields are elements at a specific level, for example msl pressure.
Any given instance of a normal field can only exist in one depiction (See <xref linkend='the_fpa_model'/>.) There are different types of fields:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Continuous fields (e.g., pressure surface heights, humidity, etc.) are modeled with splines on the FPA, instead of using the more common grid-point methods.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Vector fields are component fields like winds or waves that have both magnitude and direction.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Two-dimensional fields are areas or polygons.
Areas of clouds and weather are represented as areas on the FPA.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
One-dimensional fields are lines like fronts, ridge lines, etc.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Point fields or plot-objects, are used to display point values like surface observations.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Different graphical editors are used to manipulate one-dimensional, two-dimensional and continuous fields.
</para>
<glossseealso otherterm='g_daily_fields'>Daily Fields</glossseealso>
<glossseealso otherterm='g_static_fields'>Static Fields</glossseealso>
</glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_field_group'><glossterm>Field Group</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>field group</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Fields are grouped to make them easier to work with. Groups are defined by your system administrator. Speak to your system administrator if you prefer to see them grouped differently.
</para></glossdef> </glossentry>

</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>G</title>
<glossentry id='g_grib'><glossterm>Gridded Binary files</glossterm>
<acronym>GRIB</acronym>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>GRIB</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Major <acronym>NWP</acronym> centres (CMC, <acronym>NCEP</acronym>, <acronym>ECMWF</acronym>, etc.) distribute their model output as GRIB files that you can load into the FPA.
In Canada, CMC distributes GRIB message from the <acronym>GEM</acronym> model.
Each Weather Centre receives the national distribution as well as a set of Regional GRIB messages that contain subsidiary data that the Region has specifically requested.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_groups'><glossterm>Groups</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>groups</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Groups are field classifications.
The classification of fields into groups is a matter of office preference.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_guidance'><glossterm>Guidance</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>guidance</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Guidance comprises fields or data (e.g., <acronym>NWP</acronym> model output) that the FPA gets from remote system(s) or from allied models.
You can display, overlay and even annotate (label or draw lines on) guidance, but you cannot edit it.
Note that you can use depictions as guidance-that is, you can overlay one depiction over another to act as reference; this is useful for drawing areas of clouds and weather.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>I</title>
<glossentry id='g_interpolation'><glossterm>Interpolation</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>interpolate</primary></indexterm>
<para>
The intermediate depictions obtained by interpolating between the depictions in the sequence to some constant time interval.
Each interpolated depiction (interpolation) is a complete weather depiction itself.
In this way, you can work on charts that are spaced arbitrarily in time (e.g., 9 hours, 12 hours, etc.) and produce hourly charts.
See Sequence.
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para> Interpolations can be imported back into the depiction sequence and re-linked if necessary.
This allows you to accelerate or decelerate weather systems.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para> Some functions (e.g., text generation) require interpolated depictions.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para> Interpolations can be animated (see <xref linkend='animating_your_depictions'/>)
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<glossseealso otherterm='g_sequence'>Sequence</glossseealso>
</glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>L</title>
<glossentry id='g_levels'><glossterm>Levels</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>levels</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Levels are vertical parameters in the atmosphere such as msl, surface, 850mb or 500-1000mb.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_link'><glossterm>Link</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>time link</primary><secondary>link</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
A link is the segment joining two link nodes.
</para>
<glossseealso otherterm='g_time_link'>Time Link</glossseealso>
</glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_link_chain'><glossterm>Link Chain</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>time link</primary><secondary>link chain</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
A link chain is comprised of one or more links.
</para>
<glossseealso otherterm='g_time_link'>Time Link</glossseealso>
</glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_link_node'><glossterm>Link Node</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>time link</primary><secondary>link node</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
Link node is a point which indicates a significant feature on a depiction.
</para>
<glossseealso otherterm='g_time_link'>Time Link</glossseealso>
</glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>M</title>
<glossentry id='g_metafile'><glossterm>Metafile</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>metafile</primary></indexterm>
<para>
A metafile is a file containing "higher-order" information.
In a computer graphics context, metafiles usually contain some kind of display independent data format.
FPA metafiles are display independent, but also presentation independent.
For example, an FPA metafile would store the outline of a rain area but not what colour should be used to draw the outline.
Objects in an FPA metafile also have the geographical reference information needed to have spatial meaning on a map.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>N</title>
<glossentry id='g_normal_fields'><glossterm>Normal Fields</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>field</primary><secondary>normal</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
</para><glossseealso otherterm='g_fields'>Fields</glossseealso>
</glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>O</title>
<glossentry id='g_object_database'><glossterm>Object Database</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>object database</primary></indexterm>
<para>
An object oriented paradigm organizes data such that characteristics of an entity are encapsulated and methods of access are defined.
The objects stored in the FPA are the various meteorological fields.
It is important to note that the FPA is first and foremost a database tool with a graphical user interface (<acronym>GUI</acronym>) attached.
This fact separates the FPA from most drawing tools.
</para><para>
The FPA does not use relational database technology to store objects.
When the FPA was first developed, there was virtually no commercial spatial database technology available.
Instead a very robust system was built from the ground up for reading and writing proprietary graphics metafiles.
Specifications for the FPA metafiles are available on request.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>P</title>
<glossentry id='g_presentation'><glossterm>Presentation</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>presentation</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Presentation refers to the ways things look when displayed.
For example, line style, colour, and contour intervals are all presentation parameters.
The FPA design takes special care in making sure that users can set their own presentation parameters by means of configuration files.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_psmet'><glossterm>PSMet</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>PSMet</primary></indexterm>
<para>
A program to produce graphical products for end-users.
Use this to design your own graphical products quickly; use any graphics package to do touch-ups.
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>psmet</command>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>setup_file</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>psmet_sub_directory</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>pdf_filename</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>run_time</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_puck'><glossterm>Puck</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>editor</primary><secondary>puck</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
A rubber disc used in the game of ice hockey, an extremely popular sport in Canada.
In the context of the FPA, a puck describes a circular sculpting tool.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>R</title>
<glossentry id='g_radius_of_influence'><glossterm>Radius of influence</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>radius of influence</primary></indexterm>
<para>
The radius of influence controls the extent of smoothing which occurs when the <emphasis>move</emphasis> tool is used on a continuous or vector field.
</para><para>
The percentage indicates the affected area surrounding the point of edit.
</para> <para>
Note: Percentages range from 1 to 100 where 1 is the minimum radius of influence and 100 is approximately one quarter of the map area.
Your System Administrator establishes the exact percentage increments.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>S</title>
<glossentry id='g_sequence'><glossterm>Sequence</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>sequence</primary></indexterm>
<para>
A depiction sequence refers to the collection of depictions.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_sculpting'><glossterm>Sculpting</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>sculpting</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Modifying a line or outline using the puck tool.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_static_fields'><glossterm>Static Fields</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>field</primary><secondary>static</secondary></indexterm>
<para>
Static fields are elements which have values that are approximately constant until another static field is specified (for example, sea ice).
Static fields usually span more than one depiction.
They are not interpolated, but can be edited.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_svgmet'><glossterm>SVGMet</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>SVGMet</primary></indexterm>
<para>
A program to produce graphical products for end-users.
Use this to design your own graphical products quickly; use any vector graphics package to do touch-ups.
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>svgmet</command>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>setup_file</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>svgmet_sub_directory</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>pdf_filename</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>run_time</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>T</title>
<glossentry id='g_target_depiction'><glossterm>Target Depiction</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>target depiction</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Target Depiction defines the date and time that you want the depiction to appear in the sequence.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_texmet'><glossterm>TexMet</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>TexMet</primary></indexterm>
<para>
A program to produce tabular products for end-users.
Use this to design your own tabular products quickly; use any text editor to do touch-ups.
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>texmet</command>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>setup_file</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>texmet_sub_directory</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>pdf_filename</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req' rep='norepeat'><replaceable>run_time</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>

<glossentry id='g_time_link'><glossterm>Time Link</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>time link</primary></indexterm>
<para>
When you create a time link you are indicating that a significant feature on one depiction evolved from a significant feature on another depiction so that the FPA knows they are the same.
The FPA uses these link chains to interpolate the depictions through time.
See <xref linkend='the_fpa_model'/>.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv><title>Z</title>
<glossentry id='g_zoom'><glossterm>Zoom</glossterm>
<glossdef>
<indexterm><primary>zoom</primary></indexterm>
<para>
Lets you magnify and expand the map area graphically and pan the magnified area.
This makes it easier to work on depictions close up.
</para> </glossdef> </glossentry>
</glossdiv>
</glossary>
